<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://cmuhl.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://cmuhl.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-18T22:25:31-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/</id><title type="html">Humanist League</title><subtitle>The Carnegie Mellon University Humanist League is dedicated to building a community of humanists, who strive to improve the human condition through reason and compassion.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Truth vs. Falsehood</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/19/truth-vs-falsehood/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Truth vs. Falsehood" /><published>2018-02-19T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/19/truth-vs-falsehood</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/19/truth-vs-falsehood/">&lt;p&gt;In our every waking moment, and even in some sleeping ones, we must distinguish between what is true, and what is not. How do you determine whether your sensations reflect reality? How do you criticize the ideas that pop into your head? What do you do when presented with claims about real world from other people? Under what circumstances do you regard them as false? Under what circumstances do you regard them as true? What are the conditions that you think should make other people regard a claim as true or false?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="truth" /><category term="epistemology" /><summary type="html">In our every waking moment, and even in some sleeping ones, we must distinguish between what is true, and what is not. How do you determine whether your sensations reflect reality? How do you criticize the ideas that pop into your head? What do you do when presented with claims about real world from other people? Under what circumstances do you regard them as false? Under what circumstances do you regard them as true? What are the conditions that you think should make other people regard a claim as true or false?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goals of Parenting</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/12/goals-of-parenting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goals of Parenting" /><published>2018-02-12T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-12T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/12/goals-of-parenting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/12/goals-of-parenting/">&lt;p&gt;What are the goals of parenting? Some parents plan and make active decisions about when and how to have children, while another large percentage of the population does not. What values or guidelines should we be using to raise children? Virtually every parent wants the best for their children, but also wants their children to have the same values and beliefs as them. At what point should parents have to question their own morals for the betterment of their children? Should we allow or promote things like indoctrination? Who is to judge if parents are doing things in accordance with these goals of parenting? What resources should parents be provided and when should the government be allowed, if ever, to intervene with the act of parenting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we be trying to make children self sufficient, inquisitive, good citizens, kind, or highly intelligent? Should the goals of parenting reflect the type of society or country we are in? For example, should one of the goals of parenting be to encourage children to follow their dreams, or to work hard and be a doctor because that will be the best choice for society? Who should get to decide the goals of parenting, and will they be flexible enough to encompass a large variety of beliefs and backgrounds without being western ideals, or christian ideals etc? Some cultures value different aspects of being human than others, and have widely different parenting methods as a results. What as humanists, keeping these things in mind, should be our goals of parenting?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="parenting" /><category term="children" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">What are the goals of parenting? Some parents plan and make active decisions about when and how to have children, while another large percentage of the population does not. What values or guidelines should we be using to raise children? Virtually every parent wants the best for their children, but also wants their children to have the same values and beliefs as them. At what point should parents have to question their own morals for the betterment of their children? Should we allow or promote things like indoctrination? Who is to judge if parents are doing things in accordance with these goals of parenting? What resources should parents be provided and when should the government be allowed, if ever, to intervene with the act of parenting?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Human Love and Meaning Making</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2018/02/06/bart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Human Love and Meaning Making" /><published>2018-02-06T11:45:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-06T11:45:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2018/02/06/bart</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2018/02/06/bart/">&lt;p&gt;The son of an Evangelical pastor, Bart Campolo spent thirty years in Christian Ministry before leaving religion. Now Bart continues to work as a community builder and pastoral care provider as the Humanist Chaplain at the University of Cincinnati. Join us on &lt;strong&gt;February 6th at 4:45 pm in Margaret Morrison Room 103&lt;/strong&gt; to hear Bart talk about his journey, his work, and how he helps himself and others find meaning in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/445720055844930/&quot;&gt;Facebook event&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cmuhl.org/images/speakers/bart-poster.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Bart Campolo Poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="speakers" /><category term="meaning" /><category term="humanism" /><summary type="html">The son of an Evangelical pastor, Bart Campolo spent thirty years in Christian Ministry before leaving religion. Now Bart continues to work as a community builder and pastoral care provider as the Humanist Chaplain at the University of Cincinnati. Join us on February 6th at 4:45 pm in Margaret Morrison Room 103 to hear Bart talk about his journey, his work, and how he helps himself and others find meaning in their lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Addiction</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/05/addiction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Addiction" /><published>2018-02-05T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/05/addiction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/02/05/addiction/">&lt;p&gt;Addiction is a continued craving for the performance of a rewarding activity despite adverse consequences. It is often a reaction to stress or specific sets of environmental cues. This is different from dependence, which is when cessation of a rewarding behavior causes withdrawal symptoms. For most societies, like with the current opioid epidemic in the US, addiction is an adversary which must be overcome. Must that always be the case? Is moral judgement necessary for identifying addiction? Would it be desirable to engineer an individual or a society without addiction? If not, what role should addiction play in that society? Is it possible to engineer such a society?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="addiction" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Addiction is a continued craving for the performance of a rewarding activity despite adverse consequences. It is often a reaction to stress or specific sets of environmental cues. This is different from dependence, which is when cessation of a rewarding behavior causes withdrawal symptoms. For most societies, like with the current opioid epidemic in the US, addiction is an adversary which must be overcome. Must that always be the case? Is moral judgement necessary for identifying addiction? Would it be desirable to engineer an individual or a society without addiction? If not, what role should addiction play in that society? Is it possible to engineer such a society?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Social Anarchism</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/29/social-anarchism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Anarchism" /><published>2018-01-29T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/29/social-anarchism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/29/social-anarchism/">&lt;p&gt;Social anarchism is a political philosophy that advocates self-governed societies based on voluntary institutions. These are often described as stateless societies, or non-hierarchical associations as opposed to institutions. Anarchism holds the state to be undesirable, unnecessary, and harmful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While social anarchism is just one of many branches of anarchist theory, it emphasizes mutual aid, community decision making, and individual equality. Social anarchists advocate the conversion of present-day private property into social property or the commons, while still retaining a respect for personal property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term “social anarchism” is often used interchangeably with libertarian socialism, left-libertarianism, or left anarchism. It emerged in the late 19th century as a distinction from individualist anarchism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think of social anarchy? Can a social anarchist society viably exist? Would you support communal ownership over private ownership? Would you want to live in an anarchist community?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="anarchy" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Social anarchism is a political philosophy that advocates self-governed societies based on voluntary institutions. These are often described as stateless societies, or non-hierarchical associations as opposed to institutions. Anarchism holds the state to be undesirable, unnecessary, and harmful.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the purpose of laws?</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/22/purpose-of-laws/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the purpose of laws?" /><published>2018-01-22T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-22T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/22/purpose-of-laws</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/22/purpose-of-laws/">&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of societies have had laws of some nature, indicating that humans generally find them necessary to the operation of a society. In some cases, these laws have been for the benefit of those they govern, like property laws, and in other cases, they’ve been to the detriment, like laws forbidding American slaves to learn to read. Laws have also been based on a number of different structures. Some laws attempt to prevent concentrations of power and attempt to distribute power throughout groups of people. Others create laws from perceived rights, like the right to free speech. And different governments have also had different methods of revising laws; some forbid the governed from advocating for better laws, while others welcome the criticism to attempt to create a more equal society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern society as in historical societies, laws cover a wide range of topics. In the United States, some examples of laws are those against killing, smoking marijuana, walking around naked in public, drinking alcohol under the age of 21, stealing, invading privacy, and carrying a firearm without a permit. People differ in their opinions of the validity of some of these laws, and the purpose behind the law is not clear in all cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is the purpose of laws? To protect people from each other, from the government, or from themselves? To improve lives or control lives? Something else? What can the purpose of laws tell us about the validity of our current laws?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="laws" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The vast majority of societies have had laws of some nature, indicating that humans generally find them necessary to the operation of a society. In some cases, these laws have been for the benefit of those they govern, like property laws, and in other cases, they’ve been to the detriment, like laws forbidding American slaves to learn to read. Laws have also been based on a number of different structures. Some laws attempt to prevent concentrations of power and attempt to distribute power throughout groups of people. Others create laws from perceived rights, like the right to free speech. And different governments have also had different methods of revising laws; some forbid the governed from advocating for better laws, while others welcome the criticism to attempt to create a more equal society.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winter Book Club: The Dispossessed by Ursula Le Guin!</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/17/book-club/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Book Club: The Dispossessed by Ursula Le Guin!" /><published>2018-01-17T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-17T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/17/book-club</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2018/01/17/book-club/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who filled out the poll! The winner is The Dispossessed, by Ursula Le Guin! So grab yourself a copy of the book and read it over the winter break. We will then spend our first meeting back from break discussing the book, so be sure come with all your thoughts on Le Guin’s utopian scifi novel about capitalism versus anarchism and individualism versus collectivism!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you for a wonderful semester and we look forward to seeing you next semester!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="book club" /><summary type="html">Thanks to everyone who filled out the poll! The winner is The Dispossessed, by Ursula Le Guin! So grab yourself a copy of the book and read it over the winter break. We will then spend our first meeting back from break discussing the book, so be sure come with all your thoughts on Le Guin’s utopian scifi novel about capitalism versus anarchism and individualism versus collectivism!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection &amp;amp; Feedback</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/12/04/reflection-and-feedback/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection &amp; Feedback" /><published>2017-12-04T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-04T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/12/04/reflection-and-feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/12/04/reflection-and-feedback/">&lt;p&gt;Join us this Monday for the last meeting of the semester! Instead of a specific topic, we will spend the time collectively reflecting on what Humanist League has done this past semester. It will also be a good opportunity to hear feedback from you on how our organization has been doing. What have you enjoyed about Humanist League so far? What have you not particularly liked? What things can we improve on? What topics, events and other ideas do you have in mind for next semester?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="reflection" /><category term="feedback" /><summary type="html">Join us this Monday for the last meeting of the semester! Instead of a specific topic, we will spend the time collectively reflecting on what Humanist League has done this past semester. It will also be a good opportunity to hear feedback from you on how our organization has been doing. What have you enjoyed about Humanist League so far? What have you not particularly liked? What things can we improve on? What topics, events and other ideas do you have in mind for next semester?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Utilitarianism</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/27/utilitarianism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Utilitarianism" /><published>2017-11-27T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-27T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/27/utilitarianism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/27/utilitarianism/">&lt;p&gt;Utilitarianism is a consequentialist moral theory, meaning the core to determining what is right and wrong depends on the effects of each action we take. Utilitarians believe that the purpose of morality is to make life better by increasing the amount of good things (which can be things like pleasure or happiness), and decreasing the amount of bad, (such as pain and unhappiness).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within utilitarianism there are usually two distinctions made, between act and rule. Rule utilitarianism says that we can produce more beneficial results by following rules than by always performing individual actions whose results are as beneficial as possible. This suggests that we should not always perform individual actions that maximize utility, but instead always stay in accordance with our pre-determined rules. Act utilitarianism says that if our aim is always to produce the best results, that in each case of deciding what is the right thing to do, we should consider the available options, predict their outcomes, and approve of the action that will produce the most good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While utilitarianism is seemingly a straight forward, relying on the simple principle, do what produces the most good, it has many complexities. For instance, what is good? Do we simply measure it by what produces the most pleasure, happiness? What is happiness, how can we measure it? What are the systems or algorithms we can use to determine what options there are? What mechanism can we use to weigh these options, and make choices about them within a reasonable amount of time? These questions among others keeps the conversations open for utilitarianism as a viable system of morality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="utilitarianism" /><category term="morality" /><summary type="html">Utilitarianism is a consequentialist moral theory, meaning the core to determining what is right and wrong depends on the effects of each action we take. Utilitarians believe that the purpose of morality is to make life better by increasing the amount of good things (which can be things like pleasure or happiness), and decreasing the amount of bad, (such as pain and unhappiness).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Universal Basic Income</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/20/universal-basic-income/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Basic Income" /><published>2017-11-20T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/20/universal-basic-income</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/20/universal-basic-income/">&lt;p&gt;Universal Basic Income (UBI) is a fixed amount, at a level sufficient for subsistence, given by the state to all citizens regardless of income or work status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would cost the government $1.5 trillion to distribute $10 billion to only children and US citizens earning less than $100,000 annual (74% of the population makes less than $100,000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments for UBI include equitable and fair distribution of technological advancements; for example it may eliminate poverty and result in explosive growth in creativity, entrepreneurship, and research. While the arguments against UBI include elimination of incentives for production and work, inability of some countries to distribute funds, and global inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about UBI? If you agree with it, how much is fair? What are some of the downsides you could imagine from it? Whose responsibility is it to provide UBI? Who would benefit? Would you want UBI? If you did, what would you do with your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://futurism.com/images/universal-basic-income-answer-automation/&quot;&gt;this infographic&lt;/a&gt; for a good summary of the issue, including some case studies on its effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="universal basic income" /><category term="society" /><category term="automation" /><summary type="html">Universal Basic Income (UBI) is a fixed amount, at a level sufficient for subsistence, given by the state to all citizens regardless of income or work status.</summary></entry></feed>