<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://cmuhl.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://cmuhl.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-03T14:03:48-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/</id><title type="html">Humanist League</title><subtitle>The Carnegie Mellon University Humanist League is dedicated to building a community of humanists, who strive to improve the human condition through reason and compassion.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflection &amp;amp; Feedback</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/12/04/reflection-and-feedback/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection &amp; Feedback" /><published>2017-12-04T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-04T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/12/04/reflection-and-feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/12/04/reflection-and-feedback/">&lt;p&gt;Join us this Monday for the last meeting of the semester! Instead of a specific topic, we will spend the time collectively reflecting on what Humanist League has done this past semester. It will also be a good opportunity to hear feedback from you on how our organization has been doing. What have you enjoyed about Humanist League so far? What have you not particularly liked? What things can we improve on? What topics, events and other ideas do you have in mind for next semester?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="reflection" /><category term="feedback" /><summary type="html">Join us this Monday for the last meeting of the semester! Instead of a specific topic, we will spend the time collectively reflecting on what Humanist League has done this past semester. It will also be a good opportunity to hear feedback from you on how our organization has been doing. What have you enjoyed about Humanist League so far? What have you not particularly liked? What things can we improve on? What topics, events and other ideas do you have in mind for next semester?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Utilitarianism</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/27/utilitarianism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Utilitarianism" /><published>2017-11-27T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-27T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/27/utilitarianism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/27/utilitarianism/">&lt;p&gt;Utilitarianism is a consequentialist moral theory, meaning the core to determining what is right and wrong depends on the effects of each action we take. Utilitarians believe that the purpose of morality is to make life better by increasing the amount of good things (which can be things like pleasure or happiness), and decreasing the amount of bad, (such as pain and unhappiness).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within utilitarianism there are usually two distinctions made, between act and rule. Rule utilitarianism says that we can produce more beneficial results by following rules than by always performing individual actions whose results are as beneficial as possible. This suggests that we should not always perform individual actions that maximize utility, but instead always stay in accordance with our pre-determined rules. Act utilitarianism says that if our aim is always to produce the best results, that in each case of deciding what is the right thing to do, we should consider the available options, predict their outcomes, and approve of the action that will produce the most good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While utilitarianism is seemingly a straight forward, relying on the simple principle, do what produces the most good, it has many complexities. For instance, what is good? Do we simply measure it by what produces the most pleasure, happiness? What is happiness, how can we measure it? What are the systems or algorithms we can use to determine what options there are? What mechanism can we use to weigh these options, and make choices about them within a reasonable amount of time? These questions among others keeps the conversations open for utilitarianism as a viable system of morality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="utilitarianism" /><category term="morality" /><summary type="html">Utilitarianism is a consequentialist moral theory, meaning the core to determining what is right and wrong depends on the effects of each action we take. Utilitarians believe that the purpose of morality is to make life better by increasing the amount of good things (which can be things like pleasure or happiness), and decreasing the amount of bad, (such as pain and unhappiness).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Universal Basic Income</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/20/universal-basic-income/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Basic Income" /><published>2017-11-20T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/20/universal-basic-income</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/20/universal-basic-income/">&lt;p&gt;Universal Basic Income (UBI) is a fixed amount, at a level sufficient for subsistence, given by the state to all citizens regardless of income or work status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would cost the government $1.5 trillion to distribute $10 billion to only children and US citizens earning less than $100,000 annual (74% of the population makes less than $100,000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments for UBI include equitable and fair distribution of technological advancements; for example it may eliminate poverty and result in explosive growth in creativity, entrepreneurship, and research. While the arguments against UBI include elimination of incentives for production and work, inability of some countries to distribute funds, and global inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about UBI? If you agree with it, how much is fair? What are some of the downsides you could imagine from it? Whose responsibility is it to provide UBI? Who would benefit? Would you want UBI? If you did, what would you do with your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://futurism.com/images/universal-basic-income-answer-automation/&quot;&gt;this infographic&lt;/a&gt; for a good summary of the issue, including some case studies on its effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="universal basic income" /><category term="society" /><category term="automation" /><summary type="html">Universal Basic Income (UBI) is a fixed amount, at a level sufficient for subsistence, given by the state to all citizens regardless of income or work status.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dawkins Post-Event Discussion!</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/13/post-dawkins/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dawkins Post-Event Discussion!" /><published>2017-11-13T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-13T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/13/post-dawkins</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/13/post-dawkins/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who came to Carl Sagan Fest 2017 featuring Richard Dawkins! If you weren’t able to make it, or if you want watch it all again, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/3RIaEh7ULg8&quot;&gt;we have the video recording uploaded&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3RIaEh7ULg8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our last email we sent out a poll for the next meeting topic and the results are in! At our next meeting this Monday, we will have a post Dawkins Unplugged discussion. We can discuss anything and everything regarding what Richard Dawkins talked about on Tuesday during Carl Sagan Fest. Dawkins’ shared his thoughts on a wide variety topics, such as the selfish gene, labeling children, scientific morality, vegetarianism and pain. Did you agree with what Dawkins had to say? What questions were you left with?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="Carl Sagan Fest" /><category term="Dawkins" /><summary type="html">Thanks to everyone who came to Carl Sagan Fest 2017 featuring Richard Dawkins! If you weren’t able to make it, or if you want watch it all again, we have the video recording uploaded!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carl Sagan Fest, featuring Richard Dawkins</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2017/11/07/sagan-fest-dawkins/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carl Sagan Fest, featuring Richard Dawkins" /><published>2017-11-07T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-07T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2017/11/07/sagan-fest-dawkins</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2017/11/07/sagan-fest-dawkins/">&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3RIaEh7ULg8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us on Tuesday November 7th for Carl Sagan Fest, our annual celebration of science and human values! This year, the internationally renowned biologist and public intellectual Richard Dawkins will receive the CMU Humanism Initiative’s Carl Sagan Award. The CMU community will have a chance to hear from one of the most influential thinkers of our time while we celebrate the spirit of inquiry that animated the late Professor Sagan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be free apple pie afterwards in Rangos 3!
After all, as Carl Sagan said, “&lt;em&gt;If you wish to make an apple pie from scratch, you must first invent the universe.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/events/136330143681661/&quot;&gt;Facebook Event page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cmuhl.org/images/speakers/saganfest17-poster.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Dawkins Unplugged Poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="speakers" /><category term="sagan fest" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Affirmative Action</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/06/affirmative-action/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Affirmative Action" /><published>2017-11-06T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-06T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/06/affirmative-action</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/11/06/affirmative-action/">&lt;p&gt;Affirmative action has become increasingly more controversial over the past couple decades. One of the more recent examples can be found in the case, Fisher vs. University of Texas at Austin, in which Abigail Fisher sued the university claiming it was not granting her admission because she is Caucasian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who argue for affirmative action claim that it accounts for the additional layers of difficulty that racial/ethnic minorities and women face due to their identity. Additionally, proponents say that it corrects the disproportionate percentages of these groups in schools and industries that has come about from extreme inequality historically. Even though discriminatory actions have now become illegal against these groups, supporters say, they still face social discrimination and the impact of past discrimination is still very prominent and has yet to be corrected. They believe one way to correct such a thing is through affirmative action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, those who do not support affirmative action say that society should not be focusing on race or gender when admitting people into a certain school or workplace because it creates unnecessary tension. Instead of taking account these different identities, we should not “see” color or gender when interacting with other people in order to attain true equality. Adversaries also claim that it is reverse discrimination and that one should be admitted based only on merit, not for their race or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many universities, including Carnegie Mellon, have incorporated affirmative action into their admission process. Last year’s SCS and CIT freshman class set new records for percentage of women admitted- 48.5% and 43.3%, respectively. School officials, such as Michael Steidel and Jelena Kovačević, seem to have spoken optimistically about the results, whereas some students have expressed discontentment with the university’s decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, should affirmative action stay or be eliminated? What are the pros and cons of keeping affirmative action? If it should stay, are there cases where affirmative action is not appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="society" /><category term="racism" /><summary type="html">Affirmative action has become increasingly more controversial over the past couple decades. One of the more recent examples can be found in the case, Fisher vs. University of Texas at Austin, in which Abigail Fisher sued the university claiming it was not granting her admission because she is Caucasian.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethics of social media</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/30/ethics-of-social-media/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethics of social media" /><published>2017-10-30T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-30T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/30/ethics-of-social-media</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/30/ethics-of-social-media/">&lt;p&gt;The past decade has seen the rise of social media on an unprecedented scale. Only 13 years ago was Facebook started and today over a quarter of the world population is on the platform. Social media has impacted the way in which we connect and communicate with each other. But is this change for the better or worse? We’ve seen social media be used to overthrow governments during the Arab spring. During the last US presidential campaign we saw the spread of fake news over social media, ultimately swaying the outcome of the election. We’ve seen social media phenomena raise awareness for issues that otherwise would not have had such widespread attention from the ice bucket challenge raising awareness for ALS to #MeToo raising awareness for sexism against women. We’ve also seen social media platforms enable the rise of cyber-bulling and hate speech against individuals, even leading some to commit suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately social media platforms are created and run by business who have an incentive to engage as many users for as much time as they can. This leads them to undertake seemingly good causes like bringing the infrastructure for the internet to countries and regions and can’t afford them. However it also leads them to make their platforms incredibly addictive, one side effect being that we get shown only the content we want to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do social media companies have a moral responsibility to make their platforms vehicles for social good? What happens when their business incentives are at odds with morality? Are social media platforms simply a tool so it is we, as users of social media, that have a moral responsibility to use them for good? How can we make social media a force for good, or is that even possible?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="morality" /><category term="social media" /><summary type="html">The past decade has seen the rise of social media on an unprecedented scale. Only 13 years ago was Facebook started and today over a quarter of the world population is on the platform. Social media has impacted the way in which we connect and communicate with each other. But is this change for the better or worse? We’ve seen social media be used to overthrow governments during the Arab spring. During the last US presidential campaign we saw the spread of fake news over social media, ultimately swaying the outcome of the election. We’ve seen social media phenomena raise awareness for issues that otherwise would not have had such widespread attention from the ice bucket challenge raising awareness for ALS to #MeToo raising awareness for sexism against women. We’ve also seen social media platforms enable the rise of cyber-bulling and hate speech against individuals, even leading some to commit suicide.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assisted Suicide</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/16/assisted-suicide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assisted Suicide" /><published>2017-10-16T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-16T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/16/assisted-suicide</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/16/assisted-suicide/">&lt;p&gt;Proponents of assisted suicide think that being able to plan their own deaths helps people with unmitigatable suffering or high near-term chances of death regain control (or at least the feeling of control) over their lives. Proponents also think that planned deaths can help improve quality of life by avoiding unnecessary suffering by the person committing suicide and by her loved ones. Opponents of assisted suicide think that it stigmatizes disability, and legitimizes death as a solution to problems. Opponents are also concerned that allowing assisted suicide creates more opportunities for people to pressure themselves or others into suicides for reasons the opponents think are illegitimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morally speaking, under what situations is it permissible, or even right, to commit suicide? For which of those situations is it permissible to help another commit suicide? Given that, what should be done, both personally and through government policy, in order to make sure that permissible suicides are allowed, and that other suicides are prevented?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="suicide" /><category term="suffering" /><summary type="html">Proponents of assisted suicide think that being able to plan their own deaths helps people with unmitigatable suffering or high near-term chances of death regain control (or at least the feeling of control) over their lives. Proponents also think that planned deaths can help improve quality of life by avoiding unnecessary suffering by the person committing suicide and by her loved ones. Opponents of assisted suicide think that it stigmatizes disability, and legitimizes death as a solution to problems. Opponents are also concerned that allowing assisted suicide creates more opportunities for people to pressure themselves or others into suicides for reasons the opponents think are illegitimate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Effective Altruism</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/09/effective-altruism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effective Altruism" /><published>2017-10-09T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-09T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/09/effective-altruism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/discussions/2017/10/09/effective-altruism/">&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism is a system of using high-quality evidence and careful reasoning to work out how much good from each resource is possible. But how can you really measure your donation’s effectiveness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take for example how when we choose to go about choosing the right products to buy. We look at the reviews to find what works. Do we repeat these same procedures when we donate to charities? Do we ask about what happens to our funds when we when someone approaches us on the street?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you know your efforts are doing the most good? How can you measure the effectiveness of your charity? Do you choose local over global efforts? Do you prefer to help the most impoverished in the world over the comparatively well-off within our own country?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="altruism" /><category term="good" /><summary type="html">Effective altruism is a system of using high-quality evidence and careful reasoning to work out how much good from each resource is possible. But how can you really measure your donation’s effectiveness?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Make America Think Again: Communication Training for a Propaganda Era</title><link href="http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2017/10/04/dave-and-erin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Make America Think Again: Communication Training for a Propaganda Era" /><published>2017-10-04T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-04T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2017/10/04/dave-and-erin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://cmuhl.org/speakers/2017/10/04/dave-and-erin/">&lt;p&gt;Learn how to make reason — not fear, cynicism, or rage — the loudest voice in the room! Leave with the skills, tools, and knowledge to have meaningful political conversations that generate insights without ideological food fights. The HearYourselfThink method helps people see past media manipulation by combining critical insights into polarization and propaganda with a communication strategy that creates trust around shared values and spaces where dogma is questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founded by Dave and Erin Ninehouser, The HearYourselfThink Project is a 501c3 non-profit fighting against the harmful effects that fake news, propaganda, and misinformation have on our democracy. We’re working to make reason, not rage, the loudest voice in the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cmuhl.org/images/speakers/daveanderin-poster.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Make America Think Again Poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="speakers" /><category term="politics" /><category term="communication" /><summary type="html">Learn how to make reason — not fear, cynicism, or rage — the loudest voice in the room! Leave with the skills, tools, and knowledge to have meaningful political conversations that generate insights without ideological food fights. The HearYourselfThink method helps people see past media manipulation by combining critical insights into polarization and propaganda with a communication strategy that creates trust around shared values and spaces where dogma is questioned.</summary></entry></feed>