<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-10-17T12:12:23-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/</id><title type="html">Humanist League</title><subtitle>The Carnegie Mellon University Humanist League is dedicated to building a community of humanists, who strive to improve the human condition through reason and compassion.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Make America Think Again: Communication Training for a Propaganda Era</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/speakers/2017/10/04/dave-and-erin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Make America Think Again: Communication Training for a Propaganda Era" /><published>2017-10-04T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-04T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/speakers/2017/10/04/dave-and-erin</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/speakers/2017/10/04/dave-and-erin/">&lt;p&gt;Learn how to make reason — not fear, cynicism, or rage — the loudest voice in the room! Leave with the skills, tools, and knowledge to have meaningful political conversations that generate insights without ideological food fights. The HearYourselfThink method helps people see past media manipulation by combining critical insights into polarization and propaganda with a communication strategy that creates trust around shared values and spaces where dogma is questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founded by Dave and Erin Ninehouser, The HearYourselfThink Project is a 501c3 non-profit fighting against the harmful effects that fake news, propaganda, and misinformation have on our democracy. We’re working to make reason, not rage, the loudest voice in the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/images/speakers/daveanderin-poster.svg&quot; alt=&quot;My helpful screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="speakers" /><category term="politics" /><category term="communication" /><summary type="html">Learn how to make reason — not fear, cynicism, or rage — the loudest voice in the room</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How should we define religion?</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/10/02/defining-religion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How should we define religion?" /><published>2017-10-02T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-02T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/10/02/defining-religion</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/10/02/defining-religion/">&lt;p&gt;What is religion? What systems should we use to classify something as a religion? Most theological scholars would define religion as any system of belief or worship. While others may say that believing in a supernatural power or powers is what fundamentally makes something a religion. Should religion be defined by its practices? Should fundamentalist or fringe groups, such as Westboro Baptist Church and ISIS, still be considered religious and extended the same rights and protections as religions? What does our definition of religion mean for atheism or agnosticism, and can they counted as a religion at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does classifying certain beliefs as religion give them legitimacy in the public eye or protect them from scrutiny? Such arguments have been made about Scientology, where some would argue it is a religion, while others say it is a cult. Should we be more harsh or more inclusive in our definition of religion, and what impacts may that have on how much power they control?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, why do we care? For legal purposes, what does and does not count as a religion can have big consequences. From tax exemption, to getting days off work, to being allowed to not have your children vaccinated, beliefs with the special status of religion can have far reaching impacts on our society and day to day life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="religion" /><category term="definitions" /><summary type="html">What is religion? What systems should we use to classify something as a religion? Most theological scholars would define religion as any system of belief or worship. While others may say that believing in a supernatural power or powers is what fundamentally makes something a religion. Should religion be defined by its practices? Should fundamentalist or fringe groups, such as Westboro Baptist Church and ISIS, still be considered religious and extended the same rights and protections as religions? What does our definition of religion mean for atheism or agnosticism, and can they counted as a religion at all? Does classifying certain beliefs as religion give them legitimacy in the public eye or protect them from scrutiny? Such arguments have been made about Scientology, where some would argue it is a religion, while others say it is a cult. Should we be more harsh or more inclusive in our definition of religion, and what impacts may that have on how much power they control? Furthermore, why do we care? For legal purposes, what does and does not count as a religion can have big consequences. From tax exemption, to getting days off work, to being allowed to not have your children vaccinated, beliefs with the special status of religion can have far reaching impacts on our society and day to day life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are humans morally different from animals?</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/25/humans-animals-moral-difference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are humans morally different from animals?" /><published>2017-09-25T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-25T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/25/humans-animals-moral-difference</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/25/humans-animals-moral-difference/">&lt;p&gt;What is the difference between humans and animals? Biologically or psychologically, the differences are immediately apparent: humans have unmatched language, rationality, adaptability, cooperation, and accomplishments. However, less obvious to many is the existence of a moral difference between humans and other animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many argue that humans are not morally distinct from animals because their physical differences, such as a higher brain mass to body mass ratio than those of other animals, do not warrant moral distinction. Others argue that these same physical differences result in significant differences in morally relevant qualities like consciousness or knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the spiritual side, some argue that spiritual qualities shared among all animals render even the most physically significant differences morally insignificant. Others believe that only humans are endowed with certain spiritual qualities, like souls, that make them morally distinct from animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, a lot of disagreement on this question hinges on disagreements over what is morally significant. What is your criteria for determining moral significance? What is the value that your criteria leads you to place in animals? How does this value compare to the value that you place in humans?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="morality" /><category term="consciousness" /><summary type="html">What is the difference between humans and animals? Biologically or psychologically, the differences are immediately apparent: humans have unmatched language, rationality, adaptability, cooperation, and accomplishments. However, less obvious to many is the existence of a moral difference between humans and other animals. Many argue that humans are not morally distinct from animals because their physical differences, such as a higher brain mass to body mass ratio than those of other animals, do not warrant moral distinction. Others argue that these same physical differences result in significant differences in morally relevant qualities like consciousness or knowledge. On the spiritual side, some argue that spiritual qualities shared among all animals render even the most physically significant differences morally insignificant. Others believe that only humans are endowed with certain spiritual qualities, like souls, that make them morally distinct from animals. As you can see, a lot of disagreement on this question hinges on disagreements over what is morally significant. What is your criteria for determining moral significance? What is the value that your criteria leads you to place in animals? How does this value compare to the value that you place in humans?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Religious Naturalism</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/18/religious-naturalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Religious Naturalism" /><published>2017-09-18T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-18T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/18/religious-naturalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/18/religious-naturalism/">&lt;p&gt;For centuries, it has seemed to many that we must choose between the realism of a secular worldview and the comforts of a religious worldview.  But what if we could have both?  Suppose we combined the idea that nature is probably all there is (“naturalism”) with communities and practices designed to invoke awe, reverence, and spiritual uplift (“religions”).  Can we dispense with questionable claims about supernatural agency and still help people connect with something larger than themselves?  What would that look like?  Are there real-world examples of this phenomenon?  Do they “work” for people?  Can a thoroughly naturalistic worldview satisfy people’s need for connection, meaning, and transcendence?  If not, why not?  If so, why—and more importantly, how?  And should the result of such efforts be classified as a kind of religion?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="religion" /><category term="naturalism" /><summary type="html">For centuries, it has seemed to many that we must choose between the realism of a secular worldview and the comforts of a religious worldview. But what if we could have both? Suppose we combined the idea that nature is probably all there is (“naturalism”) with communities and practices designed to invoke awe, reverence, and spiritual uplift (“religions”). Can we dispense with questionable claims about supernatural agency and still help people connect with something larger than themselves? What would that look like? Are there real-world examples of this phenomenon? Do they “work” for people? Can a thoroughly naturalistic worldview satisfy people’s need for connection, meaning, and transcendence? If not, why not? If so, why—and more importantly, how? And should the result of such efforts be classified as a kind of religion?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What would your Utopia look like?</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/11/utopias/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What would your Utopia look like?" /><published>2017-09-11T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-11T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/11/utopias</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/11/utopias/">&lt;p&gt;From the more Utopian visions of a world like in Star Trek, Her, or Sir Thomas More’s Utopia which coined the term Utopia. To the more Dystopian visions of Blade Runner, The Hunger Games, or Orwell’s 1984. We have often thought of what our ideal world might look like. A world without suffering and illness, or poverty and greed, or a world where no has to work, or where all evil is eliminated. But perhaps Sir Thomas More was trying to tell us something about Utopia in the word he coined from the greek οὐ (“not”) and τόπος (“place”), and so Utopia means “no-place”. As the dystopian literature has shown us, a utopian vision could easily become twisted into dystopia if you’re not careful what you wish for. In many ways our ideas about utopias and dystopias tell us about the kind of world we live in and our cultural aspirations and fears, and we maybe we learn something from them that helps us move towards a real life utopia, if that is indeed something we should strive for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you could construct the world to be how you think it should, what would it look like? How would you make such a world? What might the consequences be of making the world that way? Would you want to live in that world?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="utopia" /><category term="dystopia" /><summary type="html">From the more Utopian visions of a world like in Star Trek, Her, or Sir Thomas More’s Utopia which coined the term Utopia. To the more Dystopian visions of Blade Runner, The Hunger Games, or Orwell’s 1984. We have often thought of what our ideal world might look like. A world without suffering and illness, or poverty and greed, or a world where no has to work, or where all evil is eliminated. But perhaps Sir Thomas More was trying to tell us something about Utopia in the word he coined from the greek οὐ (“not”) and τόπος (“place”), and so Utopia means “no-place”. As the dystopian literature has shown us, a utopian vision could easily become twisted into dystopia if you’re not careful what you wish for. In many ways our ideas about utopias and dystopias tell us about the kind of world we live in and our cultural aspirations and fears, and we maybe we learn something from them that helps us move towards a real life utopia, if that is indeed something we should strive for.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fishbowl</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/04/fishbowl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fishbowl" /><published>2017-09-04T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-04T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/04/fishbowl</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/09/04/fishbowl/">&lt;p&gt;Join us this Monday for a relaxed discussion on a variety of topics! Instead of having a specific topic beforehand, we will have an open discussion about any topics the group would like to discuss. So come to the meeting with a few interesting ideas you’d want to discuss. We’ll have everyone submit their topics to the &lt;em&gt;fishbowl&lt;/em&gt;, out of which topics will be randomly drawn and we’ll collectively decide if we want to talk about it, and how long to talk about it. It’ll be a fun time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="fishbowl" /><summary type="html">Join us this Monday for a relaxed discussion on a variety of topics! Instead of having a specific topic beforehand, we will have an open discussion about any topics the group would like to discuss. So come to the meeting with a few interesting ideas you’d want to discuss. We’ll have everyone submit their topics to the fishbowl, out of which topics will be randomly drawn and we’ll collectively decide if we want to talk about it, and how long to talk about it. It’ll be a fun time!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Club: Ancillary Justice by Ann Leckie</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/08/29/book-club/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Club: Ancillary Justice by Ann Leckie" /><published>2017-08-29T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-29T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/08/29/book-club</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/08/29/book-club/">&lt;p&gt;We hope you’ve enjoyed reading Ancillary Justice by Ann Leckie for our summer book club. Please join us for our first informal meeting of the year this Tuesday at 4:30 pm to talk about the book and catch up on any summer happenings. &lt;em&gt;You don’t need to have read the book to come, although there may be spoilers!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="book club" /><summary type="html">We hope you’ve enjoyed reading Ancillary Justice by Ann Leckie for our summer book club. Please join us for our first informal meeting of the year this Tuesday at 4:30 pm to talk about the book and catch up on any summer happenings. You don’t need to have read the book to come, although there may be spoilers!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Open Topic: Food and Feedback</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/05/01/open-topic-food-and-feedback/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open Topic: Food and Feedback" /><published>2017-05-01T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-01T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/05/01/open-topic-food-and-feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/05/01/open-topic-food-and-feedback/">&lt;p&gt;Join us this Monday for the last meeting of the semester! Instead of a specific topic, we will have an open discussion about any topics the group would like to discuss and collectively reflect on what Humanist League has done this past semester.  What have you enjoyed about Humanist League so far? What have you not particularly liked? What things can we improve on? What topics, events and other ideas do you have in mind for next year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be ordering pizza!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><summary type="html">Join us this Monday for the last meeting of the semester! Instead of a specific topic, we will have an open discussion about any topics the group would like to discuss and collectively reflect on what Humanist League has done this past semester. What have you enjoyed about Humanist League so far? What have you not particularly liked? What things can we improve on? What topics, events and other ideas do you have in mind for next year?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Identity Politics</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/04/24/identity-politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identity Politics" /><published>2017-04-24T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-24T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/04/24/identity-politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/04/24/identity-politics/">&lt;p&gt;We identify ourselves as belonging to many different different groups, and every group that we belong to informs our behaviors and decisions. But when should being part of a group dictate your political decisions? Can a White working class American and a Transgender African American ever vote in the same way? We have seen an increase in the use of the phrase identity politics, especially in the last election, where both sides have been accused of pandering to certain groups to gain their votes. The left has been accused of using identity politics on topics such as race, gender, and sexuality to gain the votes of those who identify as part of those groups. While the right has been said to placate the rich, white, “working-class” and religious. If you identify with one of these groups you likely feel pressured to vote for the party that seems to support your group. Even if this means that the rest of the platform you are supporting wouldn’t be something you would choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These identity informed politics often use tactics that abstract from the issues at hand, and polarize groups of people. This can become even more concerning when certain groups of people feel that they can not vote one way or another because their welfare is going to be at stake. Creating a “us versus them” mentality which creates more than political divides, but social, racial, and economic ones as well, and at that point may make us question the larger issues within our country rather than with the political parties. How do we move away from identities forming the basis of political parties and instead focus on critical debate and examination of the issues at play? At what point do political parties formed around identity groups rather than policy positions become an issue that prevents political progress?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="identity" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">We identify ourselves as belonging to many different different groups, and every group that we belong to informs our behaviors and decisions. But when should being part of a group dictate your political decisions? Can a White working class American and a Transgender African American ever vote in the same way? We have seen an increase in the use of the phrase identity politics, especially in the last election, where both sides have been accused of pandering to certain groups to gain their votes. The left has been accused of using identity politics on topics such as race, gender, and sexuality to gain the votes of those who identify as part of those groups. While the right has been said to placate the rich, white, “working-class” and religious. If you identify with one of these groups you likely feel pressured to vote for the party that seems to support your group. Even if this means that the rest of the platform you are supporting wouldn’t be something you would choose.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is wealth immoral?</title><link href="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/04/17/is-wealth-immoral/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is wealth immoral?" /><published>2017-04-17T12:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T12:30:00-04:00</updated><id>file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/04/17/is-wealth-immoral</id><content type="html" xml:base="file:///Users/akyle/Documents/hl/cmuhl.org/_site/discussions/2017/04/17/is-wealth-immoral/">&lt;p&gt;In a capitalist system, people can earn large amounts of money in a variety of ways (both moral and immoral), and once they pay their taxes, they can use or retain it however they wish. The predominate view in such a system is that these people have a right to earn money through hard work, and many people extend this to a right to retain this money as well. But is it really moral to retain that money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument can be made, as it is in &lt;a href=&quot;http://editor.currentaffairs.org/2017/04/its-basically-just-immoral-to-be-rich/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;, that retaining wealth is inherently immoral due to the vast number of people suffering due to a lack of funds. The millions or billions of dollars spent on mansions or frivolous, unnecessary goods by people with wealth could be spent paying for houses for homeless people or opening a hospital with completely free medical care to save lives. Needless deaths and suffering could be prevented without meaningfully decreasing the wealthy person’s quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the means of acquiring wealth, is it immoral to retain wealth instead of helping others? Do we even have an obligation to help others and relieve their suffering? And finally, how much money could one retain before it would become immoral to have wealth?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="morality" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="inequality" /><summary type="html">In a capitalist system, people can earn large amounts of money in a variety of ways (both moral and immoral), and once they pay their taxes, they can use or retain it however they wish. The predominate view in such a system is that these people have a right to earn money through hard work, and many people extend this to a right to retain this money as well. But is it really moral to retain that money?</summary></entry></feed>